ABU OBAIDA

4923 SE Firwood Crest Lane, Hillsboro, Oregon, 97123 979-422-9733 tareqbuet@gmail.com http://tareqobaida.github.io/

SUMMARY

4+ years of industry experience in software development with experience in the full life cycle of the software development process including requirement gathering, design, development, testing, implementation, and maintenance. Specialization in Python/Django. 6+ years of prior industry experience as a radio network optimization engineer in the telecommunication industry.

TECHNICAL STRENGTHS

Programming languages Expert in Python. Proficient in SQL, JavaScript, JQuery, Ajax,

HTML, CSS, Bootstrap. Prior experience in Java, AngularJS, VBA, C/C++, PHP. Working knowledge in React, Shell Script,

MATLAB, LISP, Verilog

Frameworks Expert in Django. Working knowledge in Flask

Data analysis & visualizationNumpy, Pandas, BokehDatabasesPostgreSQL, MySQL, OracleServeruWSGI, Nginx, Apache

Operating systems Linux(Ubuntu), MAC, Windows

Version control Git, SVN

Virtualization Docker, Vagrant

Libraries and tools Elasticsearch, Django REST framework, ServiceNow, Celery, Re-

dis, Selenium, Mulesoft, LaTeX

Cloud platform Amazon Web Services (AWS), Linode

CMS WordPress Agile tool JIRA

Protocols & APIs REST, SOAP, JSON, XML, RAML, LDAP, CAS, SSO

PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

Freelance Software Developer

July 2018 - Present

 $Self\ Employed$

- · Led the software development team in designing/developing Review Bangla a review collecting, monitoring and analyzing platform. Developed features including review and business management, personalized review invitation system, APIs and widgets, dashboard, multi-language support, etc.
- · Developed and deployed several web applications for IDARE, a Houston based Oil/Gas startup. The applications are serving diverse technical purposes for the company including the automation of finite element analysis, predicting corrosion and asset failure, analyzing data and generating reports. The applications involved diverse technologies including C, Abaqus FEA, VB, R, Excel, Python, Pandas, Bokeh, etc.
- · Led a team of three in developing *Higher Study Prep* an online educational platform. Built the online mock test and practice module for Graduate Record Examination (GRE).
- · Deployed Python/Django applications in AWS. Configured EC2, RDS, Route 53 and an Ubuntu server with Nginx+Pagespeed, uWSGI, Redis, ElasticSearch and SSL certificates.

Division of Information Technology, Texas A&M University

Lead Software Application Developer

August 2017 - June 2018 College Station, TX

- · Maintained and improved the Python/Django application of the university's Authentication & Authorization Services. Collaborated with a diverse team of sysadmins, database, backend and frontend developers and provided an uninterrupted single sign-on experience to more than 100k active users and hundreds of web and mobile applications.
- · Integrated social login with CAS (Central Authentication Service).
- · Updated the NetID (unique ID for the A&M system user) activation process involving authentication with LDAP server and developed the auto-approval process.
- · Contributed to the development of a ServiceNow application for attendance management of the university's data center.
- · Developed ServiceNow features and improved existing ones including scrum task improvement, approval notification, permission management, etc.
- · Contributed to the configuration, maintenance and upgrading efforts of the ServiceNow platform.

Technology Resources, University of Texas at Austin Software Developer/Analyst

November 2015 - August 2017 Austin, TX

- · Rebuilt the parking management system a Python/Django application leveraging the API provided by the T2 System (parking solution provider). Led a team of developers in developing, refactoring and optimizing features including permit, user and citation management, and payment processing, etc.
- · Wrote unit and functional tests for existing and new applications.
- · Participated in extensive training for REST API development using Mulesoft.
- · Designed and developed REST APIs for the university's space management application.
- · Converted a legacy PHP/Drupal application to Python/Django application.

Yu Bioinformatics Lab, Texas A&M University Software Developer (Volunteer Position)

May 2015 - November 2015

College Station, Texas

· Developed the web application for navigating metadata of publicly available mouse RNA-Seq datasets.

Texas A&M University

Jan-2014 - May-2014

Teaching Assistant

College Station, Texas

· Taught lab for cellular network planning, upgraded lab materials.

Huawei Bangladesh and Huawei Indonesia

Radio Network Planning and Optimization Engineer

October 2010 - July 2013 Dhaka and Jakarta

- · Developed and deployed a web-based monitoring and report generating application for the largest telecom swap project in Bangladesh. The application saved at least 8 man-hours daily and the report generated by the application became the de facto acceptance report for the client.
- · Acted as the team leader of the 2G radio network planning and optimization team. Led the team for VIP site optimization and customer complaint resolving.
- · Wrote a VBA program to map Ericsson radio network parameters to Huawei parameters which saved at least 4 man-hours weekly.

Ericsson Bangladesh and Ericsson Vietnam

Radio Network Planning and Optimization Engineer

January 2008 - October 2010 Dhaka and Ho Chi Minh City

- · Performed planning of base station and frequency, collected and analyzed network data to provide recommendations for optimizing the network. Led the regional team in Can Tho, Vietnam.
- · Analyzed different telecom operator networks in Bangladesh to achieve business for Ericsson.
- · Developed in-house software and data analysis tools.

PROJECT WORKS

· Developed a Python desktop application for a leading digital marketing agency in Bangladesh to automate the process of data cleaning and formatting. Saved at least 16 man-hours weekly and enabled two employees to enjoy the weekend.

AWARDS AND ACTIVITIES

- · Volunteered as an instructor for the community course "Python for Beginners", Portland, Oregon. 2019
- · Former member, PyData Austin, Austin Web Python, and The Austin Python Meetup. 2016 2017
- · Member and active volunteer, Bangladesh Student Association, Texas A&M University. 2013 2015
- · Outstanding performance award, Huawei Bangladesh. 2012
- · Full-tuition waiver in undergraduate studies for academic excellence. 2003 2007

EDUCATION

Texas A&M University, College Station, TX

May 2015

Master of Engineering in Computer Engineering, CGPA 3.68 out of 4

Bangladesh University of Engineering and Technology (BUET)

Jan 2008

Bachelor of Science in Electrical & Electronic Engineering (EEE), CGPA 3.46 out of 4

PUBLICATIONS

- M. Obaida, I. Jahan and S. Z. Sajal, "Analysis on Interactive Data Race Checker: IDRC," Presented at the 16th Annual IEEE International Conference on Electro/Information Technology (eit2017), May 14-17, 2017 Lincoln NE, USA.
- M. Obaida, E. Nelson, R. Ee, I. Jahan and S. Z. Sajal, "Interactive Sensitive Data Exposure Detection through static analysis," Presented at the 16th Annual IEEE International Conference on Electro/Information Technology (eit2017), May 14-17, 2017 Lincoln NE, USA.
- Guo Z, Tzvetkova B, Bassik JM, Bodziak T, Wojnar BM, Qiao W, **Obaida MA**, Nelson SB, Hu BH, Yu P, "RNASeqMetaDB: a database and web server for navigating metadata of publicly available mouse RNA-Seq datasets," Bioinformatics (2015)/Oxford University Press, Aug 30, 2015

WORK AUTHORIZATION

Authorized to work for any employer in the U.S.A (Permanent Resident).